<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This context.xml file has been created by the X4 Editor -->
<content id="RKI-ShipSpec" name="RKI-ShipSpecialization" description="

# Ravenknight Industries Presents: 

---
## Ship Specialization and QoL changes for VRO ( RKI-ShipSpecialization )

RKI-SS organizes some hand-picked small ships into specialized classes, including 2 newly created classes of light reconnaissance ship: Vedettes and Scanners. These ships then receive enhancements ranging from moderate to superb, based on the designated roles of their new classification. Several QoL changes too. All enhancements are balanced for VRO.
---

### Mod Information
### Name: RKI-ShipSpecialization
### ID: RKI-ShipSpec
### Author: Tax/Jonathan Ballard
### Last Updated: 4/17/22
### Current Mod Version: 0.03
### Tested with Game Version: 5.10, Split Vendetta, Cradle of Humanity, and Tides of Avarice DLC's


#### Short Description:
A mod for the game __X4: Foundations__ by __Egosoft__. RKI-ShipSpecialization (RKI-SS) organizes some hand-picked small ships into specialized classes, including 2 newly created classes of light reconnaissance ship: Vedettes and Scanners. These ships then receive enhancements ranging from moderate to superb, based on the designated roles of their new classification. Several QoL changes have been included as well. RKI-SS is intended to be used together with the incredible [__Variety and Rebalance Overhaul (VRO)__](https://www.nexusmods.com/x4foundations/mods/305) mod, which was created by _Shuul_. ShipSpecialization changes will also be applied to appropriate ships from some/all/none of the recommended mods, based on whether you install that mod. No additional mods are required. However, RKI-SS does REQUIRE all 3 Egosoft DLC's (Split Vendetta, Cradle of Humanity, and Tides of Avarice).

Recommended Mods:  

- [Variety and Rebalance Overhaul (AKA VRO)](https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=1696862840) ← ___HIGHLY___ recommended (all changes are balanced against VRO)
- [Bayamon Miner - VRO Version](https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=2647877221)
- [ATFUSC Shippack - VRO Version](https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=2627959637)
- [Ship Variation Expansion](https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=2229061492) ← Use with the VRO version below
- [Ship Variation Expansion - VRO Version](https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=2551053441) ← Requires the Vanilla version of SVE which is linked above
    - 4 SVE ships have been reclassified into the new specialized scouts
        - Akuma → Advanced Scout/Scanner
        - Paramerion → Advanced Scout/Scanner
        - Kojin → Vedette
        - Skua → Interceptor

#### Compatability (USERS):  

This mod should not have any compatability problems. It is intended to be used with VRO based on the balancing. If will edit ships from ATFUSC Ship Pack, Ship Variation Extender (SVE), and Bayamon Miner, if you have them installed.
_ShipSpecialization will automatically load itself after the mods in the recommended list (if you have them installed) to ensure that the edits are properly applied: VRO, ATFUSC Shippack, Ship Variation Extender (SVE), Bayamon Miner_


#### Compatability (MOD CREATORS):  

The mod should not cause any problems for any other mod. All changes are made through DIFF Patches. The only changes made were modifying existing values, except in the case of ship class. Ship class was defined in libraries/defaults.xml, some examples of Vanilla ship classes are ship_s, ship_m, ship_l, pretty straightforward right? The default radar range was based on these ship classes, formerly only based on ship size. To make it easier to manage radar ranges in future (so I wouldn't have to edit each ship's macro.xml file separately), and to ensure that I would only increase the radar range of the ships I wanted to (and avoid the performance hit that comes with too many ships with high radar range), I created 3 new classes (ship_scout, ship_vedette, and ship_adv_scout). These are clones of the ship_s class, except for the radar range attributes ( of which there are 2 radar range attributes for each class - one for default, and one for max).

#### Version History:
    - v0.03 (
	- v0.02 (04/14/22) - Re-organized file structure. (VRO changes applied to both VRO xml's and Vanilla xml's)
	- v0.01 (04/08/22) - Initial Commit

#### Long Description:
ShipSpecialization is designed to make interceptors and scouts feel more useful by making them perform their roles more effectively. It starts by increasing the speed of both scouts and interceptors by a solid 5-10%. Scouts then get a minor radar distance boost, and interceptors get a boost in maneuverability. I have created 3 new ship classes, all of which just re-classify existing vanilla/modified ships, and increases their radar ability. One of the new classes is just a way of differentiating scouts from other small ships so that I can slightly increase their default radar. The other 2 are only a little more involved. I have included some flavor text for the other 2 new classifications below. I don't currently have new identifying markers for them, but that's something I'd love to do, if, y'know, I was an artist. Since I'm not an artist, I'll probably leave them as they are (default ship_s icon).

##### Note:
One thing that must be kept in mind is that possibility that increasing ship radar too much can negatively affect performance. It's because of this that I'm being moderate in the increases to radar, and also increase the ship's speed, so that it can put that radar to better use.

The ships have been balanced against VRO ships, I do not currently have a Vanilla X4 version of this mod. All changes are made with the ship's minimum and maximum possible values in mind (in fact I spent more time building a spreadsheet to check balancing than I did writing the XML Diff-patches). I have also worked to include ship price into the balance equation. I found that scouts that cost 80k with 3 engines were about the same speed as ships that cost 213k with 1 engine - this didn't make sense to me. I generally went with the idea that 'more money faster ship, more engines faster ship' for base scouts and interceptors. That said, if I discover some sort of lore behind the ships that would indicate its suitability or lack thereof for its task, I would happily make use of that. 

Some ships that are classed as fighters and even a heavy-fighter or 2 have been classes as scouts, interceptors, vedettes, or advanced scouts.

I have also included several other QoL changes. These include non-combat drone speed increases, spacesuit speed and maneuverability increases, slightly increased speed of escape pods, increased tracking by 5% and cooling by 10% on Lasertower Mk.2. Increased the damage on the weapon used by Lasertower Mk.2 by 10%, but also increased the heat generated so the damage increase should only be felt on the Lasertower Mk.2.


#### Flavor text for 2 of the new classes:  

##### Vedette:  

The Vedette is a ship class designed to effect deep space patrols on their own or in 2-ship groups. They patrol the edges of systems that contain military assets to ensure that adversaries don't try to sneak into the systems and sectors without using the Gates. They are particularly important in identifying Xenon staging areas. Upon locating an enemy, they speed back to communications range and inform system/sector command.

Ship Design: Vedettes are essentially scout ships that have been stripped of everything that could be removed while remaining space-worthy, and instead installed extra radar arrays and communications equipment. Their radar ranges receive a solid increase, but they suffer in other areas, such as cargo capacity and crew chairs.



##### Advanced Scouts/Scanners:  
Excerpt taken from a smuggled copy of 'Terran Manual of Warships: Advanced Scouts': 'Advanced Scouts/Scanners are designed to outperform Vedettes in combat roles. Current doctrine states that a Vedette must disengage and flee upon contact with the enemy. With the increase in stealth technology, and the speed with which the Vedette must depart in order to deliver a warning with time to spare before the enemy arrives, often the Vedette fails to identify the precise nature of the threat, its numbers, its direction of attack, and its formation. When we have the ships to spare, doctrine allows us to pair Vedettes where the first ship arrives with the initial warning and the second returns later with more specifics. Well, why use 2 ships when 1 would do? This is where the Advanced Scout comes in. Vedettes have to sacrifice offensive and defensive power, and sometimes even the most basic amenities, in order to create space for their massive satellite arrays. Advanced Scouts/Scanners on the otrher hand are able to rely more heavily on complex target analysis and flight path prediction VI's (virtual intelligences, a lower performing but less risky varient of an AI). This allows the Advanced Scout/Scanner to sport weaponry and shielding comparable to fighters in performance, if not in price. VI's are expensive, and heavily taxed, so Advanced Scouts/Scanners are not cheap. This extra cost buys us Advanced Scouts that can stay until the last minute, gathering information and departing before the attackers can bring real threats to bear on it. Then it can simply broadcast the information from far further using the state of the art subspace communications feature of their VI.' 

Currently only the Terran factions have been able to introduce VI's small enough to fit into small ship frames. Other races still rely on more traditional scouting methods or Vedettes, though there have been rumours of a blueprint for one of the early VI prototypes that went missing from a Terran research station and found its way onto the black market. Early implementations of VI technology were viewed with extreme suspicion by the Terran populace. It's believed that the Terrans chose the term 'Scanner' to replace 'VI' in part to appease any fears of another rogue AI event. Upon the re-opening of the gates, the first Argon to encounter the ships called them 'Advanced Scouts' when they struggled to understand how a fighter could spot, target, and engage Argon scouts before the scout even knew it had company.

Ship Design: Advanced Scouts AKA Scanners are another new class of small ship. There are only a handful of them at the moment, but they receive an even greater increase to radar range than Vedettes. Performance is comparable to a fighter or heavy fighter, these ships can hold their own in a dogfight.


##### Future Plans/Ideas
1. May change out ATFUSC Ship Pack's Mobile Mining Ship engines from Large to Extra-Large  
2. Specialize Medium-sized ships as well (???)  
3. Specialize L-sized ships as well (???)  
4. Specialize XL-sized ships as well (???)  
	- Create 'Command Carrier' ship class for XL to increase visibility slightly (???)
5. 


##### Long Rant:
I'm considering working ship mass into the max speed equation, perhaps comparing it with the number of engines. This would be helpful in creating a more meaningful difference between vanguard and sentinel variants, as sentinels are much heavier. That was something I was struggling to find a reason to do. My thoughts here are that mass increases the faster you go, so you will require more fuel to continue to accelerate to a higher speed. There wouldn't be any hard math in my implementation, I might just include a 1%-10% decrease/increase depending on how many engines you have for how much mass. Since engines are more fuel efficient at lower speeds (IDK if that's true in space too, but I would think it is), the more engines you have working on smaller mass amounts, the more fuel efficient and therefore the faster your max speed can be.


#### Fairly exhaustive list of changes made:  
- Scouts  
    - Speeds increased by 5%-10%
    - Radar increased by 5% 

- Interceptors  
    - Speed increased between 2-10% (usually around 4%)
    - maneuverability increased by a flat 5% across the board.

- Vedettes
    - Class created so that their radar could be edited without affecting all small ships
    - Speed increased by 5%-10%
    - Radar increased substantially

- Advanced Scouts AKA Scanners (think of them as solid ships that were outfitted with additional sensor packages):  
    - Class created so that their radar could be edited without affecting all small ships
    - Radar increased by 25% or more
    - Speeds increased by between 5%-15%
    - Nimcha
        - Hull increased by 10%

- XL Ship Changes:  
    - Radar Increased by 10%

- Laser Tower Mk.2  
    - Tracking increased slightly
    - Damage increased by 5%

- Many Drones have had their speed increased slightly  
    - Building Drones
    - Repair Drones
    - Mining Drones (solid and liquid)

- All Spacesuit Engines have had their speed and maneuverability increased greatly  

- The Spacesuit Repair Laser has had its repair rate and range increased to make it slightly less tedious  
    - 3x Repair Rate
    - 150m Range (needs testing)

- Boarding Pods are now faster, more maneuverable, and more durable
    - Boarding Pods speed and maneuverability by between 50% and 150%
    - Boarding Pod Hull has been increased from 200 to 500 

#### Ship Groups:  
##### Scouts  
    - Pegasus Vanguard
    - Pegasus Sentinel
    - Discoverer Vanguard
    - Discoverer Sentinel
    - Kestrel Vanguard
    - Kestrel Sentinel

##### Interceptors  
    - Perseus Vanguard
    - Perseus Sentinel
    - Nova Vanguard
    - Nova Sentinel
    - Guillemot Vanguard
    - Guilletmot Sentinel
    - Elite Vanguard
    - Elite Sentinel
    - Asp
    - Asp Raider
    - Nodan Vanguard
    - Pulsar Vanguard
    - Lux
    - Kyd
    - Skua (Ship Variation Extension)

##### Vedettes
    - Kojin (Ship Variation Extension)
    - Jaguar (Split DLC: Split Vendetta)
    - Rapier (Terran DLC: Cradle of Humanity)

##### Advanced Scouts/Scanners  
    - Nimcha (Terran DLC: Cradle of Humanity)
    - Moreya (Terran DLC: Cradle of Humanity)
    - Takoba (Terran DLC: Cradle of Humanity)
    - Paramerion (Ship Variation Extension)
    - Akuma (Ship Variation Extension)


##### Links:  
- RKI-ShipSpecialization on Steam Workshop:  
- RKI-ShipSpecialization on Nexus Mods:  
- RKI-ShipSpecialization on GitHub: 
[X4_RKI-ShipSpecialization](https://github.com/JonathanBallard/X4_RKI-ShipSpecialization)
- Tax on Egosoft Forums: 
[asgardschosen](https://forum.egosoft.com/memberlist.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=462345)

https://forum.egosoft.com/memberlist.php?mode=viewprofile&u=462345
    
##### Legal:  
    
If anyone wishes to modify any portion of this mod, they may do so, so long as they credit my work, and the work of others where appropriate.  I will include the people to credit directly below this heading. No-one is to use any of my work for any commercial purposes without my express permission.  

##### Credits:  
    
- Tax/Jonathan Ballard - Ravenknight Industries (RKI) Mods  
_Thank you for being me. It's a dead-end job, and there's not a lot of perks - but somebody has to do it..._   
- Note: For clarity's sake, I am Midnightclear/Einherjarin on Nexus, and Tax/Asgardschosen elsewhere
    

##### Special Thanks To:  
    
- _Max Bain_ - Egosoft Forum Member and Creator of X4 Editor  
_Thanks for your help with how to use X4 Editor. It was by figuring out how it worked, and seeing the results, that I was able to learn to do DIFF patches._  
    
- _DeadAirRT_ - Egosoft Forum Member and Creator of DeadAir Mods series  
_Thanks for your advice and help on the Egosoft Forums_  
    
- _theqmann_ - Egosoft Forum Member and Author of the XML Patch Guide tutorial  
_Without your guide on XML DIFF's, this would have been a much much harder task. Thank you._  
    
- _Shuul_ - Egosoft Forum Member and Author of VRO  
_Thanks for creating and continuing to maintain VRO, even in the face of adversity._  



" author="Tax" version="002" date="2022-04-14" save="0" enabled="1" sync="false">
<!-- Dependencies -->
    <dependency id="ego_dlc_pirate" optional="false" name="Tides of Avarice"/>
    <dependency id="ego_dlc_split" optional="false" name="Split Vendetta"/>
    <dependency id="ego_dlc_terran" optional="false" name="Cradle of Humanity"/>

    <dependency id="ws_1696862840" optional="true" name="Variety and Rebalance Overhaul" />

    <dependency id="ws_2627959637" optional="true" name="X3 ATF/USC Ship Pack (VRO)" />

    <dependency id="ws_2647877221" optional="true" name="Bayamon Mining-Carrier" />
    <dependency id="ws_2717276439" optional="true" name="Bayamon Bergbau-Träger VRO" />
    
    <dependency id="ws_2229061492" optional="true" name="Ship Variation Expansion" />
    <dependency id="ws_2551053441" optional="true" name="Ship Variation Expansion VRO" />
</content>
